<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://karangoel59.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://karangoel59.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-06-03T04:36:46+00:00</updated><id>https://karangoel59.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Hills and Valleys of Project Management: An Insightful Journey</title><link href="https://karangoel59.com/blog/2024/project_management/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hills and Valleys of Project Management: An Insightful Journey"/><published>2024-05-31T15:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-31T15:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://karangoel59.com/blog/2024/project_management</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://karangoel59.com/blog/2024/project_management/"><![CDATA[<p>Project management, often viewed through the lens of business and technology, encompasses much more. It’s about steering a project through the highs and lows, ensuring it aligns with both stakeholder expectations and strategic goals. I recently completed a Project Management class, which culminated in a detailed study of the Recreation and Wellness Intranet Project for Manage Your Health Inc. (MYH). This experience not only provided a deep dive into project management techniques but also offered practical insights into handling real-world challenges.</p> <h3 id="the-project-at-a-glance">The Project at a Glance</h3> <p>Manage Your Health Inc., a Fortune 500 global healthcare provider, initiated the Recreation and Wellness Intranet Project with a vision to enhance employee health while reducing costs. With 25,000 employees globally, the potential impact was significant. The project, with a modest budget of $200,000 and a six-month timeline, was aimed at saving approximately $600,000 annually over four years by engaging employees in health and wellness programs.</p> <h3 id="strategic-planning-and-execution">Strategic Planning and Execution</h3> <p>From the outset, meticulous planning was critical. The project was broken down into distinct phases:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Initiation and Planning:</strong> This included everything from stakeholder interviews to detailed requirement gathering. Tools like Gantt charts and work breakdown structures were pivotal in visualizing the project scope and schedule.</li> <li><strong>Design and Documentation:</strong> Focused on developing a user-friendly interface and integrating essential health management features while ensuring compliance with data privacy laws.</li> <li><strong>Quality Assurance and Risk Management:</strong> We conducted iterative usability tests and regular security assessments to ensure the system was robust and user-friendly.</li> </ul> <h3 id="leveraging-technology">Leveraging Technology</h3> <p>Technology played a central role in managing the project. We utilized GitHub for version control and task management, which proved invaluable for tracking progress and coordinating tasks among team members. Tools like Figma and Microsoft Suite helped in designing and presenting our ideas effectively.</p> <h3 id="overcoming-challenges">Overcoming Challenges</h3> <p>The journey wasn’t without its challenges. Time underestimation and unfamiliarity with new tools led to last-minute scrambles and additional training, which were significant learning opportunities. These hurdles underscored the importance of flexible project management and the need for adaptability in the face of unforeseen complications.</p> <h3 id="lessons-learned">Lessons Learned</h3> <p>The project taught us several key lessons:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Effective Communication:</strong> Using multiple communication channels ensured that all stakeholders, including remote team members, were consistently informed and engaged.</li> <li><strong>Detailed Planning and Monitoring:</strong> Continuous monitoring of the project plan and budget was crucial for staying on track and preemptively addressing potential issues.</li> <li><strong>Success Measurement:</strong> Regularly measuring the project’s impact on employee health outcomes helped in demonstrating its value and gathering support from senior management.</li> </ul> <h3 id="personal-notes">Personal Notes</h3> <p>On a personal note, one of the standout insights from managing this project was the crucial role of incentives in driving employee engagement. Throughout various team activities, I envisioned specific outcomes and strategies; however, the willingness of group members to go above and beyond was sometimes lacking. Unlike in a real-world scenario where employees might be driven by financial gains, benefits, or a shared vision of the company’s future, in a classroom setting, these motivational factors are absent. This experience underscored the importance of aligning team members’ efforts with clear, compelling incentives that resonate with their personal or professional goals. In the academic context, the lack of such incentives highlighted the challenge of inspiring voluntary extra effort and creativity.</p> <h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3> <p>This project was more than just an academic exercise; it was a profound learning experience that highlighted the real-world applications of project management theories. The skills acquired, from strategic planning to risk management, are invaluable assets that will undoubtedly aid in any future project management roles.</p> <p>As we wrapped up the project, the satisfaction of navigating through the complexities and delivering a solution that could potentially transform an organization’s health management approach was immensely rewarding. This project wasn’t just about managing tasks and timelines; it was about fostering a healthier workplace, proving once again that at the heart of every successful project is a commitment to making a difference.</p> <hr/> <p><a href="/assets/pdf/ProjectManagement_Report.pdf">Link to the Report</a></p> <p><a href="https://github.com/kgoel59/883-project-management">Link to the Github</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="learning"/><category term="project-management,"/><category term="education,"/><category term="health-wellness"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Exploring the intricate details of managing a complex health and wellness project from a university course perspective.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Joyful Return: Lord Rama’s Homecoming in Ayodhya</title><link href="https://karangoel59.com/blog/2024/festival-thoughts/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Joyful Return: Lord Rama’s Homecoming in Ayodhya"/><published>2024-01-22T15:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-22T15:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://karangoel59.com/blog/2024/festival-thoughts</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://karangoel59.com/blog/2024/festival-thoughts/"><![CDATA[<p>Hello Everyone,</p> <p>Today marked a momentous occasion for Hindus worldwide, and as one of them, I feel compelled to share this extraordinary day with you.</p> <p>After a hiatus of 500 years, Lord Rama has returned to Ayodhya, and the experience has been nothing short of magical.</p> <p>I must admit, prior to today, I didn’t pay much attention to the temple issue. It wasn’t that I lacked devotion, but I believed that God resides in our hearts, and the absence of a physical temple shouldn’t be a cause for concern. Why create such a fuss?</p> <p>Today, my perspective underwent a transformative shift, all thanks to one thing – the smile on Lord Rama’s face. Witnessing that radiant smile on the statue made me realize that the temple was more than worth it. Even though I wasn’t physically present in Ayodhya, catching a glimpse of that smile on television created a moment of unparalleled joy, temporarily resolving all my worries.</p> <p>It seems I wasn’t alone in feeling this surge of happiness; the entire country joined in the celebration. Streets were lined with food stalls, parades, and music, turning the day into a grand festival. I’m grateful to have been in my home country for this historic occasion.</p> <p>Here’s to the beautiful smile of Lord Rama that brought so much joy to us all.</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/2024-01-22/rama-smile.jpg" alt="Rama's Smile"/></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="diary"/><category term="reflections"/><category term="hinduism"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Celebration of Lord Rama's return to Ayodhya.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Unveiling My Unique Dev Environment</title><link href="https://karangoel59.com/blog/2024/dev-env/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unveiling My Unique Dev Environment"/><published>2024-01-18T15:09:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-18T15:09:00+00:00</updated><id>https://karangoel59.com/blog/2024/dev-env</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://karangoel59.com/blog/2024/dev-env/"><![CDATA[<p>Greetings, Everyone,</p> <p>Let’s kick off today’s post with a thought-provoking question: What sets you apart? Do you perceive yourself as distinct?</p> <p>While some may confidently affirm their uniqueness, others might pause, recognizing that even as your field and interests evolve, there are numerous individuals utilizing the same tools and possessing a comparable level of expertise.</p> <p>Indeed, a dilemma exists with no straightforward answer, and responses may vary depending on whom you ask. It’s a topic that ignites psychological debates, but for now, let’s steer clear of delving into that realm.</p> <p>Allow me to rephrase the question and be more specific: As a software developer, do you see yourself as unique?</p> <p>Some may wonder, “What do you mean? What kind of uniqueness can a developer have?”</p> <p>Well, my friend, there can be many facets of uniqueness — some developers are proficient in a specific tool, some excel in a particular programming language, others have a distinctive coding style, and some are multitasking experts.</p> <p>Throughout my career working as a DevOps professional and IT enthusiast, I’ve encountered many of these unique individuals. It all boils down to how they have set up their development environment.</p> <p>Today, I’m thrilled to guide you through my development environment and the tools I use on a daily basis.</p> <hr/> <h4 id="my-requirements-and-goals-behind-the-setup"><strong>My requirements and goals behind the setup</strong></h4> <hr/> <h5 id="1-efficient"><strong>1. Efficient</strong>:</h5> <p>What do I mean by efficient? If we go by the dictionary definition, efficiency means achieving maximum productivity with minimum wasted effort or expense. So, my primary goal is to maximize productivity.</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/2024-01-18/efficient-meaning-Search.png" height="300" width="600"/></p> <p>And what is productivity for a developer - <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">coding!</code></p> <blockquote> <p><strong>Key Takeaway:</strong> <em>I need tools for coding</em></p> </blockquote> <hr/> <h5 id="2-focused"><strong>2. Focused</strong>:</h5> <p>What does focused mean? Again, according to the dictionary definition, it involves directing a great deal of attention, interest, or activity towards a particular aim.</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/2024-01-18/focused-meaning-Search.png" height="250" width="600"/></p> <p>My requirement here is a tool for <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">note-taking</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">planning</code>, I mean I need a plan to remain focused, how can I do it without that.</p> <blockquote> <p><strong>Key Takeaway:</strong> <em>I need tools for <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">planning</code></em></p> </blockquote> <hr/> <h5 id="3-durable"><strong>3. Durable</strong>:</h5> <p>The dictionary states that durability is the ability to withstand wear, pressure, or damage; it’s hard-wearing. In our context, it should be the ability of our environment to withstand disasters and system crashes.</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/2024-01-18/durable-meaning-Search.png" height="250" width="600"/></p> <p>My requirement here will be of a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">backup</code> system. As a dev, it is normal for me to upgrade the system after a few years, and there have been incidents where I lost my system completely due to an accident. So, a backup is a must.</p> <blockquote> <p><strong>Key Takeaway:</strong> <em>I need tools for <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">backup</code></em></p> </blockquote> <hr/> <h5 id="4-should-look-good"><strong>4. Should Look Good</strong>:</h5> <p>The setup should be eyes-pleasing.</p> <p>You know what a chef says, we are tempted to eat more if food looks good.</p> <blockquote> <p><strong>Key Takeaway:</strong> <em>I need tools for <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">good ui</code></em></p> </blockquote> <hr/> <p>Fantastic! Now that we’ve established our goals and requirements, creating your personalized goal list, as shown above, is the next step. Finding the right tools might seem daunting initially, but once you identify your needs, the process becomes much simpler. I recommend exploring four key places to discover tools that align with your requirements:</p> <ol> <li><a href="https://www.google.com/">Google</a></li> <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com">YouTube</a></li> <li><a href="https://github.com/topics">GitHub Topics</a></li> <li><a href="https://alternativeto.net/">AlternativeTo</a></li> </ol> <p>These platforms provide a wealth of information, user reviews, and recommendations, making your tool selection process more informed and efficient. Happy tool hunting!</p> <hr/> <h4 id="my-tools"><strong>My Tools:</strong></h4> <hr/> <h5 id="1-tools-for-coding"><strong>1. Tools for Coding:</strong></h5> <p>Over the years, I’ve experimented with various coding tools, and here’s a review for each:</p> <ul> <li> <p><strong>Notepad++:</strong> My initial coding environment, favored for writing HTML and C code. It offers basic syntax highlighting and is lightweight, but not suitable for major projects.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Visual Studio:</strong> My first comprehensive IDE for coding, used primarily for C++ projects. It delivers an excellent debugging experience but demands significant installation space and supports a limited set of languages.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Vim:</strong> Ideal for those who aim for fast coding. Vim’s key bindings and shortcuts are valuable for quick coding tasks and were my go-to for competitive programming.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Visual Studio Code:</strong> Currently, my preferred IDE, combining the features of Visual Studio with the lightness of Notepad. It supports a wide range of languages, and if there’s a specific feature you desire, chances are there’s an extension for it.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>NeoVim:</strong> Often referred to as “Vim on steroids,” but I found using Visual Studio Code with Vim keybindings extension offers a similar experience without the setup complexities of NeoVim.</p> </li> </ul> <blockquote> <p>My preference is using Visual Studio Code with Vim keybindings for a seamless coding experience.</p> </blockquote> <hr/> <h5 id="2-tools-for-planning"><strong>2. Tools for Planning:</strong></h5> <p>Planning can be a hurdle for many developers, and I’ve had my struggles as well.</p> <ul> <li> <p><strong>Notepad++:</strong> Suitable for simple note-taking but lacks advanced features.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Google Keep:</strong> Used for years, with cloud-saving capabilities, but essentially a text app.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Jira and Confluence:</strong> Highly recommended for tech companies, streamlining workflows effectively.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Obsidian:</strong> An open-source note-taking gem. While Jira and Confluence excel in collaboration, Obsidian shines for individual use.</p> </li> </ul> <blockquote> <p>Currently, I stick with Obsidian for its versatility and features.</p> </blockquote> <hr/> <h5 id="3-tools-for-backup"><strong>3. Tools for Backup:</strong></h5> <p>Every developer should have an automatic backup system on their PC to avoid the pain of losing data.</p> <ul> <li> <p><strong>Git:</strong> My primary tool for software projects, coupled with GitHub. Always remember to push your changes regularly.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>GDrive:</strong> Google’s 15GB free space is handy for file clutter. Set up GDrive for auto-sync to keep your files safe.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Mega and OneDrive:</strong> Secondary options for files I prefer not to store in GDrive, managed through some automation.</p> </li> </ul> <blockquote> <p>GDrive sync and GitHub are indispensable lifesavers; trust me, you’ll need them.</p> </blockquote> <hr/> <h5 id="4-tools-for-ui"><strong>4. Tools for UI:</strong></h5> <p>Dependent on your software choice, here are some recommendations:</p> <ul> <li>For VSCode users, enable <strong>Material Icon</strong> and <strong>Material Theme</strong> for an enhanced visual experience.</li> <li>For shell, consider trying <a href="https://ohmyz.sh/">Oh My Zsh</a>, offering cool prebuilt themes.</li> <li>A personal favorite for shell customization is <a href="https://github.com/romkatv/powerlevel10k?tab=readme-ov-file#meslo-nerd-font-patched-for-powerlevel10k">Powerlevel10k</a>.</li> </ul> <hr/> <p><em>Note: Your development environment is a reflection of your unique style and preferences. Feel free to explore and customize to make it truly yours!</em></p> <p><img src="/assets/img/2024-01-18/desktop.png" height="450" width="800"/></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="config"/><category term="projects"/><category term="learning"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Discover the intricacies of my personalized development setup.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Embarking on a New Journey: My First Blog Post</title><link href="https://karangoel59.com/blog/2024/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Embarking on a New Journey: My First Blog Post"/><published>2024-01-17T15:09:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-17T15:09:00+00:00</updated><id>https://karangoel59.com/blog/2024/blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://karangoel59.com/blog/2024/blog/"><![CDATA[<p>Greetings to everyone who has stumbled upon this page – welcome to my humble blog!</p> <p>For those unfamiliar with me, I’m Karan Goel. Proudly of Indian origin, you can call me Karan, KG, or Ken – whichever resonates with you.</p> <p>Now, you might be wondering, what’s the cause for celebration? Why am I so thrilled? The reason is simple yet significant: this site and the post you’re currently reading are officially published.</p> <p>You may ask, “What’s the big deal? The internet is flooded with countless blog posts.” True, and you’re right to wonder what sets mine apart. I’m just a software developer building a portfolio.</p> <p>Indeed, I’m not reinventing the wheel. This blog may contain familiar elements found in many others, but I’m not here to be different. I’m here for myself – for self-expression.</p> <p>As a human, I’ve always considered myself a procrastinator and a perfectionist. These traits often resulted in delayed plans and an inability to settle on anything. However, a recent revelation on New Year’s Day changed my perspective.</p> <p>I stumbled upon a LinkedIn post by a successful independent game developer friend, Nitin Verma, who shared valuable insights on achieving goals. <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/nitin-verma-a70356166_things-i-learned-about-achieving-goals-after-activity-7040347210957348865-T_ho/?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=member_desktop">Read the post here</a>.</p> <ol> <li><strong>Define Your Goals:</strong> Clearly articulate what you want to achieve.</li> <li><strong>Break Goals Into Steps:</strong> Make them more manageable and less intimidating.</li> <li><strong>Create a Plan:</strong> Develop a detailed plan of action.</li> <li><strong>Take Action:</strong> Start working towards your goals immediately.</li> <li><strong>Monitor Progress:</strong> Celebrate small wins and learn from setbacks.</li> <li><strong>Stay Focused and Motivated:</strong> Keep your eye on the prize and persevere through challenges.</li> <li><strong>Adjust Your Plan:</strong> Be flexible and make changes if needed.</li> <li><strong>Persevere:</strong> Don’t give up, every step brings you closer to your dreams.</li> </ol> <p>This struck a chord with me. I realized that I have many software projects I want to complete, but my lack of focus and perseverance often left plans on the shelf.</p> <p>Even this blog – a project planned for years – suffered from my indecision about the technology to use. Whether delving into WordPress and PHP, exploring Ghost on a server, or recently diving into Next.js, my inconsistency held me back. This blog is my commitment to change. I’ll document my progress daily and strive to make it work.</p> <p>Thank you for reading this – I’m unsure who will, but I genuinely appreciate it. Here’s to the journey ahead! 🍺</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="diary"/><category term="projects"/><category term="learning"/><category term="self-improvement"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Documenting my exploration in the realms of projects, learning, and self-discovery.]]></summary></entry></feed>